我们的星球有三分之一被冰雪覆盖
and yet, the icy worlds of the Arctic and Antarctic
然而北冰洋和南极洲的冰雪世界
are as alien to most of us as the surface
对多数人来说简直跟外星地表
of another planet.
一样奇异
They are places of superlatives.
这里充满了各种极致
From ice caps that hold nearly 80% of our planet's fresh water
从冰帽里贮藏着地球上80%的淡水
to frozen forests that encircle the entire globe.
到环绕星球一周的冰冻森林
These are places that feed our imaginations,
这些地方能引起我们的想象
places that seem to be borrowed from fairy tales.
宛如从童话中借来的一般
They're dominated and shaped by the ice...
它们由冰雪主宰和塑造
..both by its coming and by its going.
无论是因其前进还是后腿
This is our planet's last true wilderness
这是我们星球最后的真正荒原
and one that is changing just as we're beginning to understand it.
而且在我们刚刚开始了解时候 它已经开始变化
In this series, we'll be travelling to all parts of these lonely lands,
在本系列中 我们将前往 这些遍及地球南北的
both north and south,
孤寂之地
to witness its wonders perhaps for the last time
也许是最后一次见证那里的奇观
and to discover some extraordinary examples
并且要探索一些地球上
of survival against all the odds,
在最为恶劣严酷的环境下
as can be found anywhere on the planet.
生存的非凡代表
世界的尽头
The poles are permanently capped with ice.
两极有永久性的冰帽
Nowhere is colder, windier or more hostile to life.
没有哪里更加寒冷刺骨 狂风呼号 更加不利于生命
I'm standing at the North Pole - the very top of the Earth.
我正在在北极 地球的顶部
Up here, it's easy to see why the polar regions are so cold.
为什么极地如此之冷在此一目了然
The sun never rises high enough in the sky to warm my back
太阳从不会升高照暖我的后背
and those rays that do strike the surface
就连到达地表的光线
are mostly reflected back from this great whiteness.
也大都被皑皑白雪反射回去了
But the fundamental problem is that there's no sun here at all
更关键的问题是这里有整整半年
for half the year.
不见天日
The polar winter is unrivalled in its harshness.
极地的冬季严酷无比
A night that lasts for months.
慢慢长夜绵延数月
Only the toughest stay,
只有最坚韧的才会留下
as temperatures plunge to minus 70 degrees centigrade.
因为气温会降到摄氏零下70度
And yet, the greatest challenge to life here is not the cold,
但是对生命最大的挑战并非严寒
but the extreme swings between the seasons.
而是季节间的极端变化
When the sun finally returns,
当太阳终于回来后
an extraordinary transformation begins.
了不起的变化就开始了
This frozen world begins to melt away.
冰封的世界开始消融
The polar spring brings a brief opportunity for life.
极地之春为生命带来了短暂的机会
By summer, the sun no longer sets
到了夏日 太阳不再落下
and works its magic for 24 hours a day.
整天24小时不断地施展其魔法
Now it's a race to breed before the sun departs.
现在是赶在日落前进行繁殖的竞赛
By autumn, all but the hardiest abandon the poles
到了秋天 除了最坚强的都已离开
and the ice extends its grip.
冰雪的控制开始蔓延
Land and sea close down for the long, polar winter,
陆地和海洋在漫长的极地冬季里 冰封连接在一起
until, once again, the sun returns.
直到太阳再次回归
It's spring in the High Arctic
现在是高纬北极地区的春天
and the sun illuminates a giant frozen ocean,
阳光照亮了巨大的冰封海洋
the first stop on our journey.
这是我们旅途的第一站
The most powerful land predator is on the prowl.
最强有力的陆地掠食者在悄然潜行
A male polar bear is searching for a mate.
这只雄性北极熊正在寻找配偶
Willing females are few and far between
有性趣的雌性不多 都相距甚远
and the sea ice on which he travels will soon melt and vanish.
它所行走的海冰很快会消融不见
He's running out of time to find a mate in this vast, frozen desert.
它在这巨大的冰冻荒漠里 寻找配偶的时间所剩无几
Ten miles ahead, a single female without cubs -
前面十英里处 有一只没有孩子的单身雌性
exactly what the male is seeking.
正是它所要找的
He seems to relish her scent, even though she's miles away.
尽管相距甚远 它好像也很享受雌性的味道
This is an exciting prospect.
这可是机会难得
She's clearly giving off the right signals.
雌性给出的信号肯定没错
He locks onto her tracks, eager not to lose her trail.
它紧随雌性的痕迹 生怕跟丢了
It's easier to tread in the compacted snow of her footprints.
踩着雪地上的脚印会容易些
This pursuit could last for days.
这场追逐能够延续好几天
The female eventually comes into view.
雌性逐渐出现在视野里
The search is finally over.
搜寻终于结束
For the female, only half his weight,
雌性只有雄性一半重
this must be a nerve-racking encounter.
这次相遇难免心惊
The male could kill her if he chooses.
雄性要是愿意完全能够杀死它
But he has other intentions...
不过雄性另有所图
..and she is ready and willing.
雌性也满心乐意
She leads him to higher ground.
它带着雄性来到高处
It seems that courting polar bears prefer privacy,
看来求爱中的北极熊很在乎隐私
often leaving the sea ice and heading for the hills
经常离开海冰 前往山上
to avoid the prying eyes of rival males who might disturb them.
来避开可能会大煞风景的其它雄性
Few have witnessed this moment.
这一幕鲜有人见
For the male,
对于雄性
his only tender encounter in an otherwise solitary life.
这是它独行生涯中少有的温存相遇
But it doesn't last long -
不过良辰难久
a rival suitor has also caught the female's scent.
一个竞争者也循味追随而来
Courtship has to be put on hold. He must fight for his rights.
欢爱只能暂缓 它要用战斗来捍卫
He sees off this first challenger without injury to either party,
它兵不血刃地赶走了第一个挑战者
but bloodier battles are to come.
不过血的洗礼还在后面
Another battle won, though he has been slightly injured.
再战告捷 不过它也负了轻伤
He hurries back to his mate,
它赶回意中人身边
but now she seems to have lost her enthusiasm.
不过雌性好像已经没了热情
Female polar bears are high-maintenance.
让雌性北极熊满意并非易事
Wherever she goes, he will follow,
无论雌性到哪 雄性都会跟随
mating with her when she allows
雄性会随雌性心愿与之交配
and guarding her at all times.
并且每时每刻都在护卫着它
Over the next two weeks, the male sees off many rivals
后来的两周 雄性击败了许多对手
but the battles take their toll on him.
不过战斗也重创了它
He is almost spent,
它已是强弩之末
but he has ensured that no other bears have mated with his female.
不过它确保了 没有其它对手染指这头雌熊
It's time for the couple to go their separate ways.
现在它俩该分道扬镳了
She will give birth to his cubs, alone, in nine months' time
九个月之后 雌熊将独自 生下这头雄性的孩子
and he may never see her again.
而它俩可能再也不会相见
He returns to the frozen ocean,
雄性回到冰封的大海上
no doubt relieved to resume his solitary ways,
重获单身让它轻松
and just in time.
也来得及时
The ice beneath his feet will soon be gone.
它脚下的冰很快就会消失
Each spring, the Arctic Ocean undergoes
每年春天 北冰洋都要经历
an extraordinary transformation.
一次非凡的变化
An area of sea ice the size of Europe melts,
面积相当于欧洲大小的海冰消融
exposing the rich waters beneath.
露出下面富饶的海水
Short-tailed shearwaters have travelled 10,000 miles
短尾剪嘴鸥飞行上万英里
from Australia to be here.
从澳大利亚来到这里
18 million visitors darken the skies,
一千八百万鸟儿遮天蔽日
the largest gathering of sea birds on the planet.
这是地球上最大规模的海鸟聚集
Humpback whales have come all the way from the Equator
座头鲸从赤道一路赶来
to feed in these rich, polar waters.
在这富饶的极地海水中大快朵颐
Their giant tails are five metres across.
它们巨大的尾巴有五米宽
Simply raising them above the surface
仅仅把尾巴抬出水面
gives the whales enough downward momentum
就能给鲸足够的向下动力
to reach the great swarms of krill and herring below.
到达大群磷虾和鲱鱼所在之处
The shearwaters follow the giants' lead.
剪嘴鸥跟着巨鲸前进
For those who can get here, in summer,
对于那些在夏季里赶到此处的
these waters provide a feast of epic proportions.
这片水域的盛宴恢弘壮阔
But the good times will be very short -
不过美好时光总是短暂
a problem that faces all life in the polar regions.
这就是极地生命要面对的一个问题
Journeying south across the Arctic Ocean,
穿过北冰洋向南旅行
the first land you reach is Greenland,
最先来到的就是格陵兰
the largest island in the world.
这是世界上最大的岛屿
Despite its name, Greenland is mostly white,
格陵兰意思虽然是“绿色之地” 其实大部分是白色的
covered by a giant ice sheet
覆盖着巨大的冰层
six times the size of the United Kingdom.
面积相当于六个英国
In the middle of the island, the ice is nearly two miles thick.
在岛屿的中间 冰层厚达两英里
It's a bleak, quiet world.
这里是个荒凉安静的世界
Sapphire-blue melt lakes are the first sign
冰融化形成的蔚蓝色湖泊是表明
that a dynamic process is underway.
这里动态过程的第一个标志
Each lake forms in a matter of days,
每个湖泊的形成仅需几天
expanding until it's miles across and starts to overflow.
很快扩展到数英里宽并且开始溢水
The spill water then carves its way through the ice.
流出的水在冰上刻出水道
The water courses through an icy delta
水流过冰雪的三角洲
like blood along the arteries of a cold-blooded monster,
如同一个冷血怪物血管里流淌的血
a monster that is stirring.
这个怪物蠢蠢欲动
And without warning, the water suddenly plunges down an open shaft,
没有任何先兆 水流突然间冲下一个管道
falling a vertical mile into the heart of the ice sheet.
垂直落下一英里到达冰层的心脏
This meltwater has a surprising effect -
这种冰融水有一个让人惊奇的效果
it lubricates the junction
在冰层与岩床之间
between the ice and the rock floor beneath,
它起到润滑作用
so the entire ice sheet is now on the move,
所以现在整个冰层都在移动
sliding downhill into the ocean.
向下滑进大海
This, Jakobshavn Isbrae,
这个雅各布港冰川
is the fastest-flowing glacier on our planet,
是地球上移动最快的冰川
moving as much as 40 metres a day.
每天能前进40米
As it advances, it destroys everything in its path,
当它前进时 一路摧枯拉朽
even cutting its way through Greenland's great mountain ranges
在滑向大海的路上 甚至切开了
on its drive downwards towards the sea.
格陵兰岛的巨大山脉
When speeded up,
当高速播放时
these solid rivers of ice seem to flow just like liquid rivers.
这条固体河流看来与液体河流相仿
This is the titanic force
这股巨大的力量
that cuts down mountains and levels the surface of continents.
能够切开了山脉并夷平整个大陆
The ice is now entering the last stage of its descent.
冰川来到了其下降的最后一步
As it gains speed,
随着其速度的增加
huge crevasses open that extend down to its very core.
形成巨大的裂缝并延伸到其核心
It's reached the ocean,
它到达了大海
and millions of tonnes of ice have lost the support of their rocky bed.
数百万吨冰块失去了岩床的支撑
Something must give.
总有承受不住的
These icefalls are an ominous sign of what is about to happen...
这些落冰正是不祥之兆
..a rupture deep within the glacier.
冰川的深处有了裂痕
A colossal iceberg is born.
一个巨大的冰山诞生了
This single block of ice,
这一块巨冰
many hundreds of metres across,
有几百米宽
would dwarf the biggest of mankind's buildings.
让人类最大的建筑也相形见拙
Every year, tens of thousands of icebergs
每年格陵兰的冰川都会
are spawned by Greenland's glaciers,
产生数万冰山
and their number is steadily increasing
因为气候不断变暖
as the climate continues to warm.
这一数量在稳步增长
The break-up of the bergs fills the bays of the Arctic
北极的海湾里满是落下的冰山
with exquisite ice sculptures.
正如精妙的冰雕一般
It also releases great volumes of cold, fresh water into the sea.
这也为海洋带来了大量寒冷的淡水
Greenland's meltwater influences the course of the ocean currents,
格陵兰的融水左右着洋流路线
which, in turn, has an effect on the weather around the world.
这反过来对全世界的气候产生影响
The Arctic is closer to home than many of us realise.
北冰洋离我们的家园之近 是很多人没有意识到的
It includes the northernmost parts of the three continents
这里包含了多数人居住的三大洲--
on which most of us live - Europe, Asia and North America.
欧洲、亚洲和北美洲--的最北部分
The first bare land we reach on our journey south
我们南行遇到的第一片开阔地
is a bleak treeless wilderness known as tundra.
是被称作苔原的无树荒野
Each spring, animals travel up from the south,
每年春天 动物们从南面北上
to be ready for the rich grazing
好去吃到春季冰雪消融后
that will be unveiled by the spring melt.
露出来的丰饶青草
For the caribou, the timing is critical.
对于驯鹿 时机至关重要
Arrive early and a winter storm could kill you.
到得太早可能会死于冬季暴风
Delay too long and you may fail to lay down the fat
延迟太久又会来不及储存足够脂肪
needed to survive a polar winter.
来度过极地严冬
Further south still,
再向南走
and stooped, shrouded figures end the flat monotony of the tundra.
白雪覆盖的弓腰雕像 标志着单调的苔原到了尽头
This is the tree line, the first place on our journey
这是林木线 是我们途中第一处
with sufficient warmth and liquid water
有足够温暖和水分的地方
to enable a tree to grow.
所以树木能够在此生长
Surviving here is so crushingly difficult,
在这里的生存异常艰难
that it can take hundreds of years for a seedling
从树苗长到低矮的灌木
to grow into a stunted shrub.
就可能要数百年
But even small trees
不过就算小树
can provide cover for a predator.
也能为掠食者提供掩护
Wolves. These, in northern Canada,
北部加拿大的这些狼
are the largest and most powerful in the world
是世界上最强有力的
and they are setting out to hunt.
它们正准备猎食
The pack is 25 strong,
这群狼有25头之多
a sign that the prey they are seeking is formidable.
这表明它们的猎物并非易于之辈
These bison are even bigger than their southern cousins
这些野牛甚至比其南部亲戚都大
and the largest land animals in North America.
是北美最大的陆生生物
For generations, wolves and bison here
这里狼和野牛的世代斗争
have been shaped by their battles with each other,
塑造了它们各自的种群
making each the most impressive of its kind.
使得双方都成为同类中的翘楚
The bison will not stay long among the trees.
野牛不会在林中逗留过久
They're not safe here.
这里并不安全
The wolves are closing in,
狼群在靠近
but their chance of ambushing the bison in the woods has passed.
不过在林中伏击野牛的时机已逝
Their prey are now in the open and grouped together for safety.
它们的猎物已经来到了开阔地 并且为求安全聚在了一起
The wolves will need to work as a team
狼群若想成功猎杀
if they are to make a kill.
就需要团队协作
They circle the herd, trying to unsettle it and split it up.
它们绕着牛群试图使其分离
But the bison are armed and dangerous.
不过野牛武器精良 非常危险
They will be safe as long as they stick together.
只要它们聚在一起就没有危险
The wolves up their game, harrying the herd,
狼群的攻击升级 开始驱赶牛群
a ploy to trigger a stampede
这是为了促使野牛奔逃
and split away one of the smaller ones.
好把较小的从中隔离
The bison form a defensive circle around their young,
牛群将较小的野牛围在中间
horns pointing outwards.
犄角向外进行防御
The wolves need a bison to break rank.
狼群需要有野牛打乱阵型
But the tables are turning and now the wolves have to retreat.
不过整个牛群转了过来 现在狼群只能后撤
The pack focus their attention on the rear of the herd
狼群将注意力放在牛群的后部
and the bison begin to panic.
而牛群则开始慌乱
A young bison falls behind.
一头年青的野牛被拉下了
Even this yearling dwarfs the wolves.
就连这头牛犊也比狼大上许多
Running head-down, the herd's only thought is escape.
牛群低头奔跑 一心只想逃跑
A stroke of luck for the wolves.
幸运眷顾了狼群
The kill will feed the pack for several days.
这次猎杀够整群狼吃上几天
But then they will have to resume the chase.
不过之后它们还要恢复追逐
At the frozen ends of our planet,
在我们星球冰冻区的边缘
the struggle for survival never eases.
生存的挣扎从无休止
South of the tree line, the winters are shorter,
林木线的南段 冬季稍短
so trees grow faster and taller and forests begin to appear.
树木长得更快更高 森林开始显现
As the warm, humid air from the south meets the cold, arctic air,
南来的暖湿气流遇到北极的冷空气
the moisture it carries crystallises and snowflakes fall from the sky.
其湿气结晶 雪花从天而降
Each crystal forms around a particle of dust.
每片冰晶都是环绕一粒微尘形成
All have a six-fold symmetry
每一片都呈六边对称
but no two have ever been found with exactly the same shape.
但从未发现过形状完全相同的雪花
Their variety and complexity is breathtaking.
它们繁多的形态让人惊叹
Each snowflake is water waiting to be released in spring.
每朵雪花都是水滴 等待到春天被释放出来
For this reason, snow is the lifeblood of these silent forests
因此是这片寂静森林的生命之血
and all that live here depend on it in one way or another.
此处的生命都以一定方式依靠着雪
Some, like the great grey owl, appear in spring for the boom times,
一些在春天繁荣季节出现 比如这只乌林鸮
then vanish like phantoms.
之后又幽灵般消失
Others, like their lemming prey,
其它的 比如它的猎物旅鼠
are here year-round beneath the snow,
则终年生活在雪下
insulated from the cold air above.
靠雪隔开上面的冷空气
The northern forests are a crossroads
北部森林是季节性访客
for seasonal visitors and arctic specialists.
与北极区域专家的汇集处
But they are so much more than this.
不过可不仅于此
Together, they make up the taiga, an unbroken belt of forest
它们一起构成了不间断的针叶林带
that stretches 7,000 miles around our planet
环绕我们星球一周达七千英里
and contains one third of all the trees on Earth.
地球上树木的三分之一都在其中
The taiga forest marks the end of our journey through the Arctic,
从冰封的海洋到其周围的陆地
from the frozen ocean down across the lands that surround it.
针叶林带是我们北冰洋之旅的终点
The other end of our planet, the Antarctic, is starkly different.
地球另一端的南极洲则完全不同
A frozen continent completely surrounded by ocean.
这是完全被大洋包围的冰封大陆
Icebergs here are so large
这里的冰山异常巨大
that they're measured in miles not metres.
它们的测量单位不是米 而是英里
They're the only obstacles in the path of giant waves,
除了冰山 巨浪没有其它陆地障碍
which circle around the continent unchecked by other lands.
畅通无阻无阻地环绕整个大陆
These seas may be cold and storm-racked
这片寒冷的海洋也许饱受风暴袭击
but they're bursting with life.
但却孕育了无数生命
No bird is more at home in water
没有那种鸟儿在水中能更加自在
and they are masterful surfers.
而且它们是冲浪大师
Penguins are found only in the Southern Hemisphere.
企鹅只有南半球才有
They can't fly, but they don't need to.
它们不会飞 不过也用不着
There are no polar bears here.
这里没有北极熊
These are Gentoo Penguins.
这些是巴布亚企鹅
Each spring, they come ashore to lay their eggs and rear their young.
每年春天它们上岸产卵并孵育后代
Their hungry chicks demand so much seafood
它们饥饿的雏鸟要吃很多海鲜
that both parents have to go fishing.
父母双亲都得下海捕鱼
And fishing can be dangerous.
出海捕鱼会很危险
A southern sea lion.
一头南海狮
It uses the speed of a breaking wave to catch up with the Gentoos.
它利用海浪的拍击加速追上企鹅
Sea lions normally eat fish,
海狮一般吃鱼
so he's used to catching streamlined swimmers,
对捕捉流线型猎物很熟悉
but the Gentoos seem more than his match out at sea.
不过巴布亚企鹅在大海里更胜一筹
He must change tactics.
它必须改变战术
Perhaps it will be easier in the shallows.
可能在浅水里更加容易
But no! It seems penguins are uncatchable in water.
可惜不是！ 企鹅在水里似乎是捉不到的
How about on land?
那地上又如何呢？
The penguin's wings, so powerful for swimming,
企鹅的翅膀在游泳时十分有力
are of no help when it comes to running.
跑动时却全无用途
Now, surely, the sea lion has a chance.
现在海狮当然有机会
But on the beach, both are like fish out of water.
不过上了沙滩 两者都像离水的鱼
Rarely do hunter and hunted play their roles with so little skill.
猎手和猎物的技术都如此拙劣很罕见
The outcome is anyone's guess.
结果谁都无法预料
Every summer,
每年夏天
over 40 million penguins take to the Southern Ocean to feed.
超过四千万只企鹅来到南大洋觅食
They're joined by thousands of whales.
加入它们的还有数千头鲸
Minkes are the most numerous.
小须鲸的数量最多
They all come here to harvest the richest ocean on Earth.
它们都到这最丰饶的海洋进行捕猎
Carrying on south, we get our first glimpse of the frozen continent.
继续向南 就能远眺那冰封的大陆
Southern humpbacks, after travelling 4,000 miles from the equator,
南部座头鲸 从赤道开始游行四千英里
are finally arriving in Antarctica.
终于到达了南极洲
Humans have long felt the lure of this mysterious world,
很久以来人类就受到 这个神秘世界的诱惑
yet it was only a hundred years ago
但直到一百年前
that the first explorers walked inland
最早的探险者才进入其内陆
and were confronted by the highest, driest and coldest territory on Earth.
迎接他们的是地球上最高 最干也是最冷的地区
Every year, the continent is transformed
随着它周围的海冰开始消失
as the sea ice that surrounds it begins to disappear.
每年这片大陆都会变化
This melt halves the size of Antarctica.
消融面积有半个南极洲大
It's the most spectacular seasonal change
这是我们星球各地季节性变化中
occurring anywhere on our planet.
最令人叹为观止的
The remnants of the sea ice are occupied by sunbathing seals
海豹们占领了剩余的海冰来晒太阳
that have been here all winter.
它们在这里度过了整个冬天
But new arrivals are following the retreating ice edge
不过猎手也尾随消退的冰缘到来
and they have come here to hunt.
它们是来猎食的
Killer whales, the ocean's top predator.
它们是虎鲸 海洋中的顶级掠食者
Killers are like wolves,
虎鲸如同狼群
for they will hunt animals far larger than themselves.
它们会猎食远比自己大的猎物
But even smaller prey are a problem if you can't reach them.
但够不着的话 连小猎物都是问题
The solution is teamwork.
解决之道就是团队协作
Swimming in perfect formation, they flick their tails in unison
它们排成整齐队列 一起摆动尾巴
and create a wave that cracks the ice.
形成的波浪让冰块破裂
They regroup and assess the damage.
它们重新集结来观察破坏效果
A more powerful wave is needed.
还需要更有力的波浪
The ice floe is breaking up.
浮冰已经碎裂
Now they are close enough to get a good look at their target.
现在它们能好好观察一下目标了
The seal is a crabeater, sharp-toothed and feisty.
这是食蟹海豹 牙齿锋利而且好斗
Not their favourite.
不对它们的胃口
The wolves of the sea move on in search of easier quarry.
海中的狼群继续前进 去寻找容易些的猎物
A Weddell seal. That's better.
一只威德尔海豹 这好多了
These are more docile and easier to tackle.
它们更加温顺 也更容易捕捉
The pod stays close together and travels silently.
鲸群靠在一起悄然前行
This time, they unleash a far more powerful wave,
这次它们形成的波浪有力得多
and with astonishing accuracy.
而且异常准确
These big waves are not intended to break the ice,
这些大浪不仅用来击碎浮冰
but to knock the prey into the water,
而是要把猎物打到水下
and they rarely fail.
它们很少失手
The seal is now where the killers want it,
海豹现在的位置正合虎鲸之意
but the hunt is far from over.
不过狩猎还远未结束
They need to grab their prey by the tail
它们需要从尾部抓住猎物
while avoiding its snapping jaws.
以防被其咬到
Only then will they be able to pull it down and drown it.
只有如此才能拉住猎物并将其淹死
Sideswipes create violent underwater turbulence, a new tactic.
侧划能产生猛烈的水下乱流 这是它们的新战术
Blowing bubbles gives cover for others to lunge at the seal's tail.
吹出气泡来掩护同伴扑向海豹尾部
Somehow, the seal manages to reach a tiny ice floe.
海豹奋力爬上了一小块浮冰
The killers could easily grab it,
虎鲸能够轻易地抓住它
but now this seems to have become a game.
但是这似乎已经成了一场游戏
The seal's life hangs on a roll of the ice.
海豹的生命全部系与这块浮冰
Yet again, the pod joins forces to dislodge the seal.
然而 鲸群再次合力将它推下
The seal sees a chance to escape.
海豹看到了逃跑的机会
Exhausted, it no longer has the energy to pull itself to safety
它精疲力竭 没法把自己拖到安全区
and the killers are moving in.
而虎鲸则在靠近
Game over.
游戏结束了
Although such team hunts are rarely seen,
这样的团队狩猎十分少见
scientists believe they may be the most complex
科学家相信这是从自然界记录下的
ever documented in the natural world.
最复杂的狩猎行为
They were first witnessed by Captain Scott and his men
斯考特船长和他的手下在一百年前
when they came to explore Antarctica 100 years ago.
来南极洲探险时最早见证了这一幕
Journeying further south, the fragmenting ice is replaced
继续向南 破碎的浮冰变成了
by a permanent sheet that doesn't melt even at the height of summer.
连盛夏也不会消融的永久冰原
It's a barrier that many creatures find impassable.
这对很多生物来说不可逾越
It repels even powerful minke whales.
连有力的小须鲸对这也束手无策
They have to turn back
因为无法呼吸到
if they can no longer reach the air they need to breathe.
必须的空气 它们只能忘冰止步
Under the ice, life has to be extremely specialised to survive.
冰层下的生命要十分特化才能生存
Few of us will ever experience this strangely-still world,
能体验这宁静奇境的人少之又少
and, as yet, no-one knows much about it.
而且人们对这里所知甚少
The crystalline surface of the ice stalactites
冰钟乳的结晶表面
provides a home for ice fish whose bodies are full of anti-freeze.
是冰鱼的家 它的身体满是防冻液
The ceiling of ice shields those living below it
顶部的冰层为下面的生命提供庇护
from the violent polar weather that rages above.
使其免受极地严酷气候危害
Little here has changed for millions of years.
这里几百万年都没什么变化
The cold allows animals to grow very slowly and become giants.
动物在寒冷中生长极其缓慢 并且成为庞然巨物
A relative of the woodlouse is the size of a dinner plate.
土鳖虫的亲戚能有盘子般大
And this so-called "sea spider" has legs that span half a metre.
这个被叫做“海蜘蛛”的家伙 腿展开后有半米宽
Now explorers are revealing other worlds
现在探索者开始探索另一个世界
that lie hidden beneath the ice on land.
它就在藏在冰雪下面的陆地之上
These smoking towers are the gateway to a network of caves.
这些烟塔是一个洞穴网络的门户
Each contains an extraordinary assembly of ice crystals,
每个都是晶莹剔透的水晶宫
unlike any other on Earth.
不是凡间所在
Like snowflakes, every crystal is unique.
与雪花一样 每簇冰晶都独一无二
Some are taller than a man.
其中一些有一人多高
Others are thought to harbour life,
人们认为有一些中含有生命
seeded by strange bacteria that thrive in these extreme conditions.
是在这样极端条件下繁盛的细菌
The breeze that gently sways these crystals
微风轻轻地摇曳着这些冰晶
is responsible for making them.
正是它创造了它们
It's steam from the molten heart of Mount Erebus,
这是来自埃里伯斯火山心脏的蒸汽
the most southerly volcano on our planet.
该火山我们星球上最靠南的火山
It's now thought that the ice caves fringing this crater
人们现在认为这火山口边缘的冰洞
may even be a home for hitherto-unknown life forms.
可能有迄今尚不为人知的生命形态
From this oasis of warmth at the edge of the continent,
从这大陆边缘的暖洲开始
our journey continues inland towards the South Pole.
我们继续向内陆的南极点进发
The first great hurdle
第一个大障碍
is the formidable Transantarctic mountain range.
就是可怕的南极横断山脉
We are following the route taken by Scott and Amundsen
我们沿斯考特和阿蒙森的路线前进
as they struggled to become the first humans
他们曾为成为最先到达南极点的人
to reach the South Pole.
而激烈竞争
They were travelling on foot
他们是靠步行
and their first sight of these mountains
他们第一眼看到这些山峰之时
must have been daunting indeed.
一定也心生怯意
In front of them stretched one of the world's longest ranges,
他们面前是世界上最长的山脉之一
spanning 2,000 miles from one side of the continent to the other.
跨越两千英里 横亘整个大陆
The winds up here are the fastest on Earth.
这里的风速世界最高
They reach speeds of 200 miles an hour.
时速可达200英里
An ice-capped mountain bears the scars of the gales,
狂风在冰雪覆盖的山峰留下了疤痕
bizarre sculptures carved from solid ice.
坚冰被刻成了奇异的冰雕
It's not only the ice that yields.
不仅坚冰为此屈服
This sculptured spire is the remnant of a mountain,
这塔尖般的风雕是一座山峰的遗迹
eroded from all sides by the ferocious elements.
被凶猛的狂风从四周侵蚀而成
Beyond, a wholly unexpected landscape - the dry valleys.
翻越山脉之后是意想不到的景色 干燥的峡谷
Only 1% of Antarctica is free of ice,
南极大陆只有不到1%没有冰雪覆盖
and most of that bare rock is here.
多数裸露的岩石都在这里
The Dry Valleys are more like the surface of Mars
干峡谷更像火星的地表
than is any other place on Earth.
而不是地球上的地方
The floor is covered with extraordinary natural sculptures,
谷底有许多奇异的自然雕塑
created by the same winds that help to keep these valleys free of snow.
创造出它们的风也让这里没有冰雪
Over time, entire boulders are weathered from the inside out,
经年累月 整块巨石被从中心风化
until just a shell remains.
直到只剩外壳
At the head of these valleys, the ice is making a breakthrough.
在峡谷的尽头 冰雪终于有所突破
Millions of tons are tumbling in slow motion into the valley.
数百万吨冰雪缓慢地落入山谷
These ice blocks are the size of skyscrapers.
这些冰块大小相当于摩天大楼
And this is the Beardmore Glacier,
这就是比尔德莫尔冰川
which Scott and his men somehow traversed on foot.
斯考特和他的队员步行穿越这里
It's over 100 miles long
它有一百多英里长
and one of the largest glaciers on Earth.
是世界上最大的冰川之一
But nothing could have prepared those early explorers
但是早期探险者们怎么也无法为
for what they were about to encounter.
他们下面要遇到的做出准备
The Antarctic ice cap, the largest expanse of ice on the planet.
南极冰帽 地球上覆盖最广的冰体
It's three miles thick in places
有些地方厚达三英里
and imprisons 70% of the world's fresh water.
贮藏着地球上70%的淡水
From here to the South Pole 700 miles away,
从这里到南极点的七百英里
there is nothing but ice.
除了冰以外一无所有
I'm at the South Pole at the end of my journey.
我正在南极点 也是旅途的终点
Although it's midsummer, the temperature here
尽管时值盛夏 这里的气温
is a bone-chilling 35 degrees below freezing.
仍是刺骨的零下35度
It's exactly a hundred years almost to the day
从第一人站在这里到今天
that the first human beings stood right here,
几乎整整一个世纪
Amundsen followed by Scott.
先是阿蒙森 斯考特紧随其后
In those days, reaching the poles
在当时 到达极点
was regarded as the ultimate in human endeavour and endurance,
被认为是人类努力和忍耐的极限
and a source of great national pride.
也会成为国家的骄傲
Today, the polar regions have a rather different significance,
现在极地区域的重要性大不相同
because now we've come to understand that what happens here
因为我们今天已经了解了这里
and in the north affects every one of us,
和北极地区对每个人的影响
no matter where we live on this planet.
无论我们居住在何地
雪骨冰神--拍摄花絮
The greatest challenge for the team making Frozen Planet
摄制组拍摄冰冻星球最大的挑战
was the extreme remoteness of their locations.
是他们极度偏远的位置
Many of the shoots lasted months at a time
很多拍摄延续数月之久
and needed a number of crews to join forces.
也需要几个小组联合行动
One location that would require such siege tactics
需要这样协同作战的一个地点
was Mount Erebus, Antarctica's most active volcano.
就是埃里伯斯火山 南极洲最活跃的火山
This magical mountain does not give up her secrets easily.
这神奇的山峰不会轻易透露其秘密
火山的秘密
To capture the full story of Mount Erebus from top to bottom
为了从山顶到底下拍摄到 埃里伯斯火山的完整故事
required four different film crews.
就需要四个不同摄制组
The cave team is dropped off at 12,000 feet, close to the crater.
冰洞组在一万两千英尺高处的 火山口附近降落
In howling winds and thin oxygen,
忍受着呼号的狂风和稀薄的氧气
their challenge is to find a way into the volcano itself.
他们的挑战是如何找到进火山的路
They are venturing into the unknown.
他们在走进未知
Somewhere below are spectacular ice caves, melted out by volcanic steam.
要去这火山蒸汽融化出来的 壮丽冰洞中的某处
Getting the team safely underground
摄制组安全抵达地下
is a relief for director Chadden Hunter.
让导演柴顿·亨特送了一口气
Excellent, it's much warmer down here, it's freezing up there.
好极了 下面暖和多了 上面冻死了
Minus 29.
零下29度
With him is cameraman Gavin Thurston.
跟他一起的是摄像盖文·瑟斯顿
You sort of forget being in here, you are actually inside a volcano.
到这儿就好像忘了自己在火山里了
You know, above us and below us, there's bubbling lava
我们上面和下面都有熔岩
and you've got all these gases seeping up through here,
这里有这些蒸汽透出
which is how these caves are made,
这就是冰洞形成的原因
so there's also increased carbon dioxide in here.
这也导致了这里二氧化碳的增加
As the cave team head deeper,
随着冰洞组向洞穴深处前进
dangerous volcanic gases make breathing difficult.
危险的火山气体让呼吸变得困难
The clock is ticking.
他们的时间不多了
They will not have long to find the caves of crystals.
他们得尽快找到晶莹的冰晶洞穴
Above ground, the aerial team is pushing for the summit of Erebus.
在上面 航空组正在努力 靠近埃里伯斯火山山顶
Series producer Vanessa Berlowitz directs from the front seat,
本系列制片维尼萨·波洛维兹 在前排指挥
while aerial cameraman Michael Kelem
同时航空摄像迈克尔·凯尔曼
controls the camera attached to the nose.
操纵附在机鼻上的摄像机
We're going to be around 14,000 feet,
（飞行员保罗·墨菲）
我们将到达一万四千尺高度
on the performance limits of this aircraft.
是这直升机的操作极限
Any bad weather comes in up there
要是那里有任何坏天气
and you're pretty much screwed, really,
你们基本就完了 真的
you've got to get off the mountain fast.
你们得迅速下山
Above 10,000 feet, the pilot must breathe oxygen
一万英尺以上 飞行员要通过
through a plastic tube in his nostrils.
连到他鼻孔的塑料管吸氧
Approaching the crater, conditions do not look good.
他们在靠近火山口 情况并不乐观
Today, Erebus is belching out steam and gases,
今天埃里伯斯火山喷出蒸汽和气体
making flying extremely risky.
让飞行有极大风险
Up here, the air is so thin, the helicopter can't hover
这里空气太稀薄 直升机不能悬停
and must keep moving.
必须不停移动
This is aerial filming at its most extreme.
这是航空摄像的最大极限
They struggle to get a clear view.
他们在努力寻找清晰的视野
We're just coming up to 14,000 feet,
我们到了一万四千英尺
you can actually look right into the lava lake.
你们能正好看到熔岩湖
Oh, that's looking really good, Mike, just hold that there.
看来不错 迈克 抓住这图像
The cameraman captures a rare shot of the molten lava,
摄像师抓拍到了难得一见的熔岩湖
but it's soon obscured again.
不过很快视野又模糊了
The volcano is temperamental.
火山让人捉摸不定
The team have seized a rare opportunity
摄制组把握住了鲜有的机会
to see into its molten heart,
看到了其熔融的心脏
but now they must descend to safety.
不过现在他们要降到安全高度了
As the weather closes in above, the cave team are making progress below.
上面的坏天气就要来了 但冰洞组有了进展
It's Christmas Day and the crew are dressed for the occasion.
这是圣诞节当日 组员也有所打扮
Just watch my back on these icicles,
看这我背上这些冰晶
I don't want to snap that top one off.
我可不想把上面的撞掉
How strong are these pillars of ice?
这些冰柱能有多结实？
- It's about... - Round about five...
- 大概...
- 直径有5...
So if I squeeze past, it's not going to snap it?
要是挤过去 应该不会弄断它吧？
Gavin is reassured by advice from the scientist.
科学家的建议让盖文放心
Ohhh! Gavin!
哦！盖文！
I'm sorry.
不好意思
That's terrible. Oh, look, it fits perfectly, look. Look at that.
真糟糕 看 对齐了 看哪
Fortunately, these crystals are made of frozen water
所幸这些晶体是水冰冻而成
and can grow back in weeks.
几周后就能恢复
You've got these beautiful, clear, glass-like pillars
这些玻璃般的柱子美丽清澈
and right next to it, this really delicate...
它旁边这个真是精致
Look how thin that filament is there.
看这丝状物非常纤细
As the cave team explore deeper,
冰洞组向深处探索
each chamber reveals ice crystals
这些冰室里的冰晶
more strange and spectacular than the last.
一个比一个奇异瑰丽
No-one on the team imagined a single Antarctic mountain
没人能想到一座南极的山
could house so many wonders.
会有这么多奇观
Down at the foot of Mount Erebus, a third crew, the dive team,
第三个摄制组潜水组则在火山脚下
plan to explore the volcano's lower slopes,
他们要去探索火山下面
which extend beneath the frozen sea.
延伸到冰海里的底坡
On board is underwater cameraman Hugh Miller.
机上是水下摄像休·米勒
The problem is, we don't actually know what's under the ice here.
问题是我们不知道冰下会有什么
So who knows, it's a bit of an adventure.
谁知道呢 这就是探险
Old-fashioned tools still work best.
老式工具仍然很好用
First, a hand chisel to create an opening,
先用钢钎凿开冰
then a saw to widen the hole.
之后用钢锯加大开口
Ice-diving in the coldest waters on the planet
在地球最冷的水域冰下潜水
should be taken extremely seriously.
千万要多加小心
This dive's going to be a lot of things
这次潜水里有很多元素
and warm is not on that list.
温暖可不在其中
Insulated suits will keep them alive under the ice for only 60 minutes.
绝缘服仅能保证他们 在冰下生存一个小时
Once the helicopter departs, there's no margin for error.
直升机飞走后就容不得一丝差错了
The dive team begin to explore the lower slopes of Erebus,
潜水组开始探索埃里伯斯火山底坡
discovering a hidden world rarely seen by humans.
发现了少有人见的隐秘世界
Patrolling the icy shores of the volcano are killer whales,
沿着火山冰缘巡弋的的是虎鲸
the most southerly in the world.
是世界上最南部的种群
Tracking them from above is the orca team.
在上面跟踪它们的是观鲸组
They need a helicopter to get ahead of the whales
他们要用直升机赶到虎鲸前方
and to land them on the fragile sea ice.
并上到脆弱的海冰之上
Cameraman Jamie McPherson must pick his spot carefully.
摄像杰米·麦克泊森得谨慎选址
His aim is to get the cameras
他的目标是把摄像机
as close to the killer whales as possible without disturbing them.
尽量架设到离虎鲸近的地方 又不能打扰它们
He uses a film camera to capture the action in slow motion.
他用胶片摄像机来捕捉慢动作
And the orcas come right by him.
虎鲸们就从他身边经过
Even in the extreme cold,
就算在极度严寒之中
a film camera proves to be rugged and reliable...
胶片摄像机还是性能可靠
provided there's enough film in the camera.
只要胶片够用就行
- End of the run. - No!
- 这卷到头了
- 不！
I've got him coming out, I just didn't get him going back in.
我刚拍到它出来 没拍到它回去
All right!
好了！
Below the sea ice, the dive team is setting up an underwater studio.
潜水组在海冰下建立了一个工作站
Using a range of waterproof lights and time-lapse cameras,
他们希望利用防水照明和延时摄影
they hope to capture the growth of bizarre underwater ice formations.
来捕获奇异的水下冰晶形成过程
Over the coming weeks,
接下来的几周
the dive team would go below the ice over 100 times
潜水组将要潜到冰下100多次
to film the extraordinary secret world
来拍摄埃里伯斯火山底部
on the lower flanks of Mount Erebus.
非凡的冰下神秘世界
On top of the ice, the orca team has repositioned.
在冰上 观鲸组又重新部署了
Their new goal is to get underwater shots of the whales.
新目标是拍摄虎鲸的水下镜头
They don't dare to get in the water with orcas.
他们可不敢进到有虎鲸的水里
Attaching a camera to a pole is a safer option,
把摄像机绑到杆子上就安全多了
provided the whales aren't put off by it.
只要虎鲸们不受干扰就行
No-one is prepared for what happens next.
接下来发生的谁也想不到
Tell her what you just saw.
告诉她你刚才看到什么了
The entire pod arrives.
整群都来了
Eyeball to eyeball,
视线相接
this is about as close to killer whales as it's possible to get.
这大概是跟虎鲸的最近距离接触了
By using multiple crews and cameras, the Frozen Planet team
冰冻星球制作团队 通过使用多组成员和摄像机
have been able to capture the full Erebus story, from the fire
完整地记录了埃里伯斯火山的故事 从它山口的火焰
at its crater down to the whales that patrol its frozen shores.
到在其冰岸游弋的鲸群
It's quite a privilege to feel whale breath on your face.
脸上感到鲸喷出的气息真是荣幸